<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Holy confidence well improved, by Nehemiah and the Jews whose faith and spirit were considered and applied to the societies for reformation of manners : in a sermon at Salters-hall in London, on Monday August 16, 1697, and now at their request made publick / by Matthew Sylvester.</title>
            <author>Sylvester, Matthew, 1636 or 7-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12443576</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12443576</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62163</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62090)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62163)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 948:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Holy confidence well improved, by Nehemiah and the Jews whose faith and spirit were considered and applied to the societies for reformation of manners : in a sermon at Salters-hall in London, on Monday August 16, 1697, and now at their request made publick / by Matthew Sylvester.</title>
                  <author>Sylvester, Matthew, 1636 or 7-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>viii, 61, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Darby, for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[3] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62163:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Holy Confidence Well Improved, BY <hi>NEHEMIAH</hi> and the JEWS: Whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and applied to the SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIETIES for <hi>Reformation of Manners;</hi> in a SERMON at <hi>Salters-hall</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> on Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <hi>Auguſt</hi> 16, 1697. And now at their Requeſt made publick.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Matthew Sylveſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Cui ſapit ipſe Deus, ſolus ſapit ille. Quid haeres?</l>
               <l>Ad res difficiles dum vocat, ipſe praeit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Darby,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62163:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:62163:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS Divine Providence hath exceeded all our Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Deſerts by the Vouchſafement of a moſt Grateful <hi>Peace</hi> in theſe Parts of <hi>Chriſtendom:</hi> and as the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath greatly us'd and proſper'd the Agency and Conduct of our moſt Gracious and Illuſtrious Soveraign
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:62163:3"/> King <hi>WILLIAM III.</hi> in this great Acqueſt, to his Immortal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Renown; in all which God ſeems to be upon his way to bring great Things to paſs: ſo what can more <hi>concern</hi> us, and <hi>become</hi> us, than to meet <hi>this Providence,</hi> and <hi>his Majeſty,</hi> in that Spirit and Courſe which may beſt correſpond with thoſe great Obligations and Deſigns which are hereby laid upon us, and ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us? Sad and portentous would it be, and a Preſage of dreadful Judgments in reverſion, if a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd Generation from all the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of deſolating and expenſive Wars, ſhould yet continue to wage War with Heaven, by uncontrouled Immoralities, Debaucheries, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God knows yet how to diſtreſs us more and more, either by Wars, or by other Judgments of equally diſmal Conſequence thereto, to us. What ſignifies our Peace with Men, if we have none with
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:62163:3"/> Heaven? The Lord of Hoſts can neither <hi>need</hi> nor <hi>want</hi> fit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Engines of Diſtreſs to plague us with, when he once finds that neither <hi>Peace</hi> nor <hi>War</hi> will bring us to that dutiful and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Reformation, which he ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently doth attempt to <hi>fright</hi> and <hi>court</hi> us to. Fain would I hope that this Deſign of Reformation is on foot; and that ſuch a Spirit is kindled amongst us as will invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorate all fit Endeavours to bring this thing to paſs, and that too, under Divine Countenance and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. And my Hopes are the more ſtrong and free, in that I find ſo many of different Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to external Diſcipline and Worſhip, to be ſo evidently one in this important matter. I think I have ſeen all the Sermons preach'd before the Societies for <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Manners</hi> hitherto: and I have read them with great Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:62163:4"/> and to my no ſmall Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. I find them all breathing the ſame true Chriſtian Spirit; and I muſt tell my Brethren, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conformiſts or Diſſenters, that I cannot but eſteem and reverence that Judgment and Savour which I have diſcern'd in their ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and pertinent Sermons. I ſtrongly hope that the nearer we all come to God and Chriſt by Faith and Holineſs, the more of Peace and Love we ſhall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence amongst our ſelves. And the more evident we ſhall render it to all Men, that we can differ in our Sentiments about the Modes of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Worſhip, and yet most dearly love each other. I do not <hi>hate</hi> nor <hi>cenſure</hi> thoſe of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren whom I differ from, ſo many of whom I find ſo very much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my ſelf in Parts and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Practical Chriſtianity. I reverence all proportionably to their
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:62163:4"/> diſcerned Excellencies. Chriſt hath his valuable and uſeful Inſtruments in each Communion. O that we could but love and treat each other as Chriſt himſelf doth and will love and treat us all! Why ſhould I hate or ſlight any below on Earth, whom I expect and am well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that I ſhall love and live withal in Heaven above? I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do, nor can expect much Good from any inordinate Heats or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotry, where-ever fixed and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed; as knowing well who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that <hi>the Wrath of Man works not the Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> Sound Faith, orderly Lives, peaceable Principles and Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, cordial Affections, with all fit Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilities of Converſation, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Abhorrence of all Countenance to the Works of Darkneſs; may theſe, <hi>Candid Reader,</hi> be ever dear to thee, and to thine, in and for the ſake and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Intereſt of
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:62163:5"/> tke Great Lord of Holineſs, Peace, and Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>Sept. <hi>27. 1697.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Matthew Sylveſter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62163:5"/>
            <head>Holy Confidence Well Improved.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>NEHEM. II. 20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then anſwered I them, and ſaid unto them, The God of Heaven he will proſper us; therefore we his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants will ariſe and build.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="1">§. 1. GREAT Enterprizes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſeveral things to make them in their appearances like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and more particularly ſuch things as theſe. 1. Good Warrant, that they may be juſtifiable. 2. True Conduct, that they may be orderly. 3. Noble Spirits, whereby they may work their way through all the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and Oppoſitions which in all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62163:6"/> likelihood will attend them: for as the Enterprize will deſerve the Spirit, ſo ſhould the Excellence of the Spirit be conſpicuous in the Enterprize, which is to be managed by that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. 4. Right Ends; ſeeing all Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Undertakings are ſpecified, and ſo either ennobled or debaſed by their Ends. For it is a ſort of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of any Undertaking that looks well, and appears worthy in the matter of it, to be proſtituted to any Deſigns or Ends inferiour to the Perſon and his Work. 5. Thorow Diligence, Watchfulneſs, and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Diligence</hi> reſpects <hi>Difficulty,</hi> and is oppos'd to <hi>Wearineſs;</hi> and he that grows weary is not likely to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his end. <hi>Watchfulneſs</hi> relates to, and connotes ſurprizing <hi>Danger;</hi> and good Beginnings may be baffled by unthought-of Hindrances. <hi>Confidence</hi> ſpirits Courage; and great things are <hi>encountred bravely</hi> where Succeſs may be in proſpect, through peculiar Help. 6. Clear and impartial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings all the way. Irregular ſteps are moſt diſhonourable things. Means and Motions ought to be anſwerable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62163:6"/> to their Ends, and evidently worthy of them. No truly ſinful Steps can here be juſtified; for whatever God calls us to, he neither needs Lies nor Wickedneſs, nor any thing forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, as in its own nature unworthy and unwarrantable (no more do we) to bring ſuch things to paſs, as God ingages us to purſue. And therefore, 7. All muſt be done with evident and great regard to God, and to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good. <hi>To God;</hi> (as to his <hi>Name, Will, Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi>) there muſt be ſolemn and ſober Addreſſes to him, and great Submiſſions to his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Pleaſure. There muſt be continual Dependence upon him; mighty, but well-grounded Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from him; judicious and well-temper'd Zeal for him; and (in a word) uniform Faithfulneſs and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votedneſs to him, and to the Publick Good; as <hi>of</hi> him, by his Order; <hi>under</hi> him, as to his Conduct and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and <hi>to</hi> him, as to his Glory, as to juſt Repreſentations of him to our ſelves and others, wherein we may expect him to appear; and as to all ſit Teſtimonies of our Reſpects to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62163:7"/> him. To all which I may add, 8. There muſt be <hi>Self-denial</hi> in all fit Inſtances and Engagements. As to the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> it ought to be dearer to us than our own perſonal Concerns. For this indeed, if it be deliberately, vigorouſly, and ſucceſsfully promoted, one way or other, the Benefit and Honour will be greatly ours. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiveneſs in any of theſe things will hazard, and may fruſtrate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat the moſt glorious Undertakings, and dreadfully expoſe the Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. I did not ſeek to be God's Mouth to you, and yours to him, this day: yet did not I much withſtand your Offer, becauſe my Heart is in your worthy Work. For I well know, (and ſo doth God himſelf) that you might have choſen far better Heads and Hearts than mine, for your Inſtruction and Encouragement, as from the Mouth of God. But as you have choſen the Mouth, ſo God has ſent the Meſſage, if I miſtake him not, and far be it from me <hi>to talk deceitfully for him.</hi> The Lord enable me to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62163:7"/> ſpeak as from his Mouth, and as it <hi>becomes the Oracles of God,</hi> that I may appear before and to you, (as once a Prophet long ſince did, <hi>viz.) As the Lord's Meſſenger in the Lord's Meſſage to you, ſaying, The Lord is with you, Haggai</hi> 1.13. For all our Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments, Aſſiſtances, Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Succeſſes, muſt be deriv'd alone from him.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. It looks not a little hopefully upon us, that ſo many worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (rather of different Names than of contrary Spirits and Deſigns) have ſo concentred their Hearts and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, in a Matter ſo full of God, and ſo evidently for him, as this appears to be, in my moſt ſerious and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Thoughts. The World, I hope, will hereby ſee, that our Hearts are one in God and Chriſt, and for their Glory and the publick Good, tho we have ſome different Sentiments about Excentricals: And I will (and I dare be free to) ſay, that thoſe excellent, learned, and ſerious Perſons, both of the Clergy and Laity of the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, who have concern'd themſelves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62163:8"/> in this Affair, have hereby ſhew'd their Readineſs to ſtrengthen each others hands for God, and are now reſolved to run down (if poſſible) thoſe Immoralities, Blaſphemies, and Debaucheries, which give ſuch bold and fatal Strokes at our publick Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and Renown. Whereupon I muſt and do profeſs, that as thereby they have been moſt commendably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary to our ſelves and others, ſo have they moſt deſervedly entitled and endear'd themſelves to our beſt Affections and Reſpects. How much more lovely is it in the ſight of God and Man, to ſee Conformiſts and Nonconformiſts vigorouſly to engage themſelves to caſt out all the Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh of Profaneneſs, and practical Diſorders, (which is diſowned by the Laws of God and Man, and has been frequently diſcountenanc'd in theſe Kingdoms, by publick <hi>Acts</hi> and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts) than by their Tongues and Pens to diſpute and write each other into ſuch dangerous, unaccountable, and unwarrantable Diſtances, Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Diſcords! And I am pleas'd to ſee in this Affair ſuch eminent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62163:8"/> Proofs, that in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> there are more excellent and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſons, than ſtrait-lac'd and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious Spirits may poſſibly imagine. To cleanſe, to build, to fortify for God, under the Calls, and in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of our preſent Day; and under ſuch Countenance as our preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Laws afford us; O! what more worthy of our Thoughts and Pains? what more delightful to the views of ſerious Chriſtians? and what more awful and accountable to the Enemies of God and Chriſt, of ſerious Religion, and of the publick Good?</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. As to the <hi>choſen Text,</hi> it will not appear ſo very foreign in its Senſe and Import to the Deſign and Buſineſs of this Day, as the haſty Reader, or raſh Hearer, may poſſibly imagine at the firſt view, if a few things be well conſidered: <hi>viz.</hi> that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Tranſgreſſions of this People had brought them to their terrible and diſgraceful Deſolations and Diſperſions; <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.7. ch. 9. 26—37. Of this <hi>Jeremy</hi> gives us
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62163:9"/> a very <hi>great</hi> account in his ſo mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lamentations. See alſo 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.19, 22. And indeed the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures abound with lively and copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Repreſentations and Aſſurances of this thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Till they were penitent, and concernedly intent upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation-work, their Deliverance and Reſtoration were not reaſonably to be expected by them. <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.40—42. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.11. Deliverances and Salvations muſt we not look for to the Diſhonour of the God thereof, nor to the Diſadvantage of that holy Kingdom and Deſign, which the Son of God hath been, and is endeavouring to promote and finiſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They all grow ſenſible hereof: <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.6—11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.32—35. No Sins now unlamented, and no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation now declined by them. A wicked, ſlothful, and hard-hearted People, are not receptive of what they ſeem to covet: but when they lie down in Tears and Shame before their God, and clothe themſelves with Reſolutions to do no more ſo fooliſhly, but to walk more worthy of that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62163:9"/> Divine Preſence which they ſo much affect and need; then their very Temper and Deportment moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably preſages their Mercies and deſired Salvations to be near them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Their preſent Work and Aim is to prepare for the Memorials and the Reſidence of their God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.1—9. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.15—9. They had now known the Import of a preſent and departed God to them. They knew and felt, that when God's Temple is demoliſh'd, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s Walls and Houſes could not ſtand; for God's Departure is impregnated with great Woes to them that loſe him. The <hi>Sheekinah</hi> always bears its own Charges; and where 'tis wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, it makes Bleſſings of all kinds and ſizes to be plentiful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Walls, Temple, City, and the Peoples Habitations there, muſt be deſign'd (as they well knew) for ſomething elſe; 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.12—14. They could not be inſenſible, of whom they were themſelves; of what a God they had to do with; and to what purpoſes he and they were to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62163:10"/> come and dwell together there; yea, or in what Frame and Courſe they and their God were to converſe and keep together. Hence <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> builds the Temple: <hi>Ezra</hi> endeavours to reform the People; and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> builds <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s Walls and Gates to ſecure all within. For who can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſuppoſe that Temple, City, and People, ſhould be thus provided for, and ſo induſtriouſly ſecur'd without juſt reference to their God? Surely it had been much below <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s excellent Senſe and Spirit, to mind a People, and to ſlight their God; <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14.—18. A Man would think, that the Seventy had their eye upon this thing by their thus rendring the Text: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. We are his pure Servants: <hi>Perfectly ſeparated from Gentile Vanities, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely conſecrated and conſigned to our God:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>we will build,</hi> as it becomes ſuch Servants, <hi>i. e.</hi> pure Votaries to our God: ſo far are we from thinking or deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing abſtractedly from him. And the Arabick Verſion repreſents them as ſenſible hereof, that God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62163:10"/> would therefore proſper them, his Servants, that they might ariſe and build.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. In the Text therefore are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable theſe things to be conſider'd. 1. The confident Perſons, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and his People. 2. Their grounded Confidence; <hi>The God of Heaven will proſper us.</hi> Wherein we ſee what they conceiv'd concerning him: That he is <hi>God;</hi> the God of <hi>Heaven; their</hi> God; for they call themſelves his Servants. This they were <hi>ſure</hi> and <hi>ſenſible</hi> of; they thence inferr'd the Certainty of their Succeſs. 3. The Reſolution grounded thereupon; <hi>We will ariſe and build.</hi> 4. The Influence of their profeſſed Faith on this their purpoſe; <hi>therefore we will,</hi> &amp;c. 5. The free Profeſſion of all this; <hi>Then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered I, and ſaid to them.</hi> And here conſider <hi>by whom</hi> it was made. 'Tis a diſcourag'd and ſcorn'd Seed in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane view, tho order'd and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by their God. To whom? To <hi>Sanballat, Tobijah, Geſhim,</hi> thoſe contemptuous Scorners. <hi>What</hi> they profeſs'd; where; when; and why.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62163:11"/> 6. The Uſefulneſs of this Text to us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I. The Confident <hi>Perſons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt; Nehemiah,</hi> whoſe Name im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports Comfort from God unto his Servants; whoſe <hi>eminent Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> for this Work have their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videncing Inſtances in abundance; whoſe <hi>Heart</hi> was greatly ſet upon his Brethren and Work; and whoſe <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>Encouragement</hi> was wonderful from God and Providence. Indeed <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Son of <hi>Shealtiel,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Son of <hi>Jozadack,</hi> (the Prophets at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> helping them) they ſet about the Temple to prepare God's Houſe for him, that ſo the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Reſidence of his Name might be fix'd and kept amongſt them: <hi>Ezra</hi> 5.2. Then <hi>Ezra</hi> ſets up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reforming the People by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Prayer, and proper Counſel and Perſwaſion; <hi>Ezra</hi> 9, <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſets upon the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the City-Walls and Gates, for the ſecurity of God's Houſe, City, and Servants; and to prevent the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62163:11"/> Reproaches of the Heathen; <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.17. All theſe improve their Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Advantages from the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of Authority, and from the Counſel and Encouragement of God's Prophets with them; and all the Remnant of the People in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective places fall in with them to promote this Work of God, when thus accommodated for it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to it; <hi>Haggai</hi> 1.12—14. But then, not only <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> but alſo,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly;</hi> His People with him, were accompliſhed for this great Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking; <hi>Haggai</hi> 1.14.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> their <hi>Leader,</hi> and the <hi>great Promoter</hi> of this bleſſed Work, he was hearty and concern'd; ſenſible of God's Judgments, and the Peoples Sins; acquainted and affected with their doleful Caſe and State; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votional and ſerious with God for his good hand upon them in what they undertook; more devoted to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Religion, and of the publick Welfare, than to his own Honour or Inrichment: Valiant and vigilant to go through with what was now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62163:12"/> on him: Prudent and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in managing Things and Perſons to the beſt advantage: Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in pertinent Conſultations about emergent Difficulties and Dangers: Generous in his Contributions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the promoting of this great Affair: and every way provident for Unanimity and Reformation: Much ſet upon it, that the Houſe be fit for God, that the People ſuit God's Preſence there, and that all be duly guarded.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to the <hi>People: They had a mind to work,</hi> Neh. 4.6. They <hi>ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their Hands</hi> for the Work, <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Their Eyes were up to God,</hi> Neh. 4.9. They were <hi>receptive</hi> of <hi>Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>attentive</hi> to the <hi>Law,</hi> Neh. 8.3. and they adher'd to God and to their Superiours, <hi>Neh.</hi> 10.29.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. The <hi>Confidence</hi> of theſe <hi>Perſons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>More generally;</hi> that what they were about was according to God's Heart: that it was pleaſing to him: that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and his People were thus concern'd about a Temple and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62163:12"/> People worthy of him, and about their Preſervation in that State; that it was according to his Order; that it was according to God's Promiſe; that it was for his ſake, that he might dwell among them, be glorified by them, and appear glorious, and look like himſelf in every eye, to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual reſcuing of his City, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Name, and Servants, from the Reproaches of the contemptuous Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. For how dreadfully did it look, to ſee a People, peculiarly God's, to be without God, and God himſelf to be without his Temple, and without thoſe reverent Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Addreſſes from his People, and without thoſe practical Regards to him, which might diſtinguiſh them from others, and ſhew to all with what a holy God they had to do? They were alſo confident that God had ſpirited them for this thing; <hi>Haggai</hi> 1.14. and that his Preſence was their Countenance and Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. They had his Prophets to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them; they had fit Leaders to influence them, and their own Spirits were prompt and reſolute
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62163:13"/> to and in all thoſe Endeavours and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendances, and Purſuits, which were now ſo conſpicuous amongſt them. They were well ſatisfied that God would ſhew himſelf to be the <hi>God of Heaven,</hi> and proſper them, <hi>anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> to their relation to this God; and that God himſelf would treat them as the <hi>Servants of the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> It was evident that he fix'd amongſt them his Interceſſors for them continually to mind him of them: And that he had poured out the Spirit of Prayer upon them. They had no doubt about <hi>God's Name,</hi> about <hi>their Relation</hi> to him, their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in him, their <hi>Call</hi> from him, their <hi>Concern</hi> for him, their being <hi>countenanced</hi> by his Providence; nor about the genuine <hi>Reference</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviency</hi> of what they now reſolve upon, <hi>unto God's Glory,</hi> and to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation</hi> and <hi>Renown</hi> of their <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But more <hi>particularly,</hi> 1. The <hi>Matter</hi> of their Confidence was, that <hi>God would proſper them: i. e.</hi> firſt, they ſhould compleat their Temple, City, Walls and Gates. That then their God would keep his Reſidence, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62163:13"/> amongſt them. That God would countenance, promote, accept their Reformation, according to his Grant and Order, both in Church and State. That he would in and from his Holy Temple be their Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Guard, and Joy. That he would there accept their Suits and Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; give them ſuch Anſwers and Returns as they ſhould truly need; and thereby greaten both Himſelf and Them in publick view, to the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of all about them. That conſequently no Enemies Attempts upon them to defeat their Work and Purpoſe ſhould be proſperous. And that all this ſhould end in the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Lord of Glory, in his Goſpel-living Temple. O! had the City, Temple, Walls, and Gates, been built, and no God there; or had the material Buildings bounded and terminated their Deſires, their Building had been vain, and they themſelves unfit for the Patronage, Preſence, and Protection of the God of Heaven; neither had their Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſneſs in their preſent Enterprize been really a Bleſſing to them. Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62163:14"/> and People without God and Godlineſs, without Devotion and Religion, how mean would the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and the Succeſs have been? How thin the Poſſeſſion? How diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and reproachful the Succeſs?</p>
               <p>Secondly, The <hi>Ground</hi> of this their Confidence, <hi>that they ſhould be proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous;</hi> was, 1ſt. God's Eminence, as the God of Heaven. Heaven is God's Throne and Reſidence; and it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents him as above all, and over all; and able to accompliſh and diſpenſe what he thinks ſit. 2dly. God's <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> unto them. How many encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging Relations to this People doth God own, whilſt he calls them, his <hi>Portion, Children, Subjects, Heritage,</hi> and <hi>Jewels?</hi> 3dly. God's <hi>Preſence</hi> with them: Witneſs his Spirit, Prophets, Providences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4thly. God's own <hi>Concern</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> in this their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Work: for he deſign'd them to be the People of his Preſence, Choice and Joy, and accordingly by ſpecial Favours to ſignalize them as ſuch. And, 5thly. His <hi>antient Promiſe</hi> to them. And, O! what Holds are theſe for Faith and Hope? How will
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62163:14"/> they animate and invigorate our Prayers and Confidence, our Diligence and Reſolution, when we are called out to act for God!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>III. Their Reſolution hereupon.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>We will ariſe and build,</hi> Neh. 2.17, 20. They fix their Purpoſes. They thought it not enough to mourn, faſt, pray, profeſs, or ſeriouſly to repreſent their Caſe to God: Nor would they heſitate or deſiſt. God needs not us, but we need him. Yet if there be any Abilities, Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, Opportunities, Warrant and Encouragements, our order'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince is to be minded by us, and our determined and appointed Work re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon: For Reſolution is to iſſue into Action. This turns and fixes the bent and biaſs of our Souls and Motions. Man is fit for nothing, till Reſolution ſets him out: Men unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved are unſtable; <hi>James</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This we will do, <hi>as we are God's Servants,</hi> and <hi>becauſe</hi> we are ſo; <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.10, 11. <hi>Ezra</hi> 5.9—11. All muſt be done <hi>by order</hi> from on high, <hi>in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62163:15"/> of</hi> it, and <hi>according to</hi> it. They did not look upon their preſent Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and Employment as an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing; as if it were left with them whether to build or no; or to build as they liſt. God's Will and Favour were the great Enforcements of this Purpoſe. Humour and Will did not here thwart or baffle Conſcience; but all lay proſtrate at the foot of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as that reſpected God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Order; and all was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and directed by that regent Principle. Men do not otherwiſe act <hi>as Servants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Their high and awful Thoughts of God gave Life and Spirit to this their worthy Reſolution; and well it might; for where God is, all muſt be proſperous: Nothing can ſtand againſt him, or before him, to defeat his Purpoſes and Counſels. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31. <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.9. They ſaw whoſe Patronage, Help and Preſence they might rely upon. This made them fixed and fearleſs, and unwearied till their Work was done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62163:15"/>
               <head>IV. The Influence of their Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon their <hi>Purpoſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. This made their Reſolution to be <hi>rational: Therefore</hi> we will build. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Reſolution will be conſtant. 'Tis no ſmall ſatisfaction to know up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what Ground we ſtand; or what we enterprize, and why. What! ſuch a God! ſo great! ſo wiſe! ſo good! ſo true, and faithful! We <hi>his</hi> Servants! and ſuch Succeſs in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect! What are Enemies, Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Coſt or Pains hereto!</p>
               <p n="2">2. This <hi>fix'd</hi> their Purpoſes at once. The Cogency hereof could not but preſerve an equal Tenour; for God is evermore the ſame. He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can deny himſelf, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. They had here the ſame cogent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and Motives to urge their continuance in their Work, which they had to prompt them to begin it. Clear Apprehenſions of God's Immutability will greatly eſtabliſh the Reſolutions of his Servants.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This ſweetned all their Pains and Dangers, and ſet their ſpeedy, joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62163:16"/> End and Iſſue in their clear and conſtant Proſpect; for all their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that oppos'd this thing, did but expoſe themſelves thereby. None can be proſperous, they knew, that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd themſelves againſt the God of Heaven; nor can that Work miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor that Hope prove abortive, which God eſpouſes, and attends with a propitious Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>V. The fit and free Profeſſion of all this.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The Profeſſors were a deſpiſed and diſcouraged Seed, under Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for their Crimes. God had let looſe their Enemies upon them, and ſuffered them to lay all waſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; and the Spirit of Enmity againſt them in their Enemies was not yet extinct; <hi>Ezra</hi> 5.12. <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.17, 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.1—4, 8, 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.36, 37. <hi>Jeremy</hi>'s <hi>Lamentations</hi> afford us a ſad Mirrour of their dreadful and deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Condition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The things profeſſed by them were all diſtaſteful to their Heathen Enemies: Their <hi>Faith,</hi> that their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62163:16"/> God was in Heaven, where Pagans Gods are not: Their <hi>Relation</hi> to this God, that they were <hi>his Servants,</hi> and therefore ow'd no Service to their Pagan Gods: Their <hi>Reſolution,</hi> that they would ariſe and build for God; for they'd admit no Rival nor Peerage with their God in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern: which made this good Man briskly tell his Enemies, that they had <hi>no Memorial, Right,</hi> nor <hi>Portion</hi> in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi> As for God's Grandeur in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and his Reſidence and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in his Temple there, this they knew would eclipſe all their Pagan Glories. And then <hi>their gathering to their own Land</hi> could not be pleaſing to their inſulting Enemies. And, laſtly, Their <hi>profeſſed Confidence</hi> in this God, and their <hi>expectation of Succeſs from him,</hi> ſeem'd to import, yea, plainly ſpake it, that they took their Adverſaries to be as nothing in God's hands; <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This they profeſſed, when moſt oppos'd and ſcorn'd; <hi>Then</hi> anſwer'd I them. Something of parallel hereto we find in <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16—18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.6—10. They acted now, as under the Senſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62163:17"/> and Power of what we have upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.12—14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 41.10—16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51.12, 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 40.25—31.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They had great Purpoſes and Reaches in their eyes in this Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.14—16. <hi>&amp; Ezra</hi> 5.11, 12. This their Profeſſion ſeems to be animated by that Spirit of <hi>Love,</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> and of a <hi>ſound Mind,</hi> which we find mentioned in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. And it look'd well and providently every way. 1ſt. Toward <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; As the God that they would ſanctify, and had ſo profound a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to: this ſpake them tender of his Honour, and heartily devoted to the glorifying of his Name. For they hereby were ſolicitous that all ſhould know, that the God of Heaven, and of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had no Equal. 2dly. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected greatly on <hi>God's</hi> Enemies: For did they know the God which they confronted by hindring the Builders and the Building, they would rather roll themſelves in Duſt, than engage their Tongues or Hands againſt that Being which ſo infinitely tranſcends them. 3dly. It look'd greatly at the <hi>once captive,</hi> but <hi>now returning</hi> Jews.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62163:17"/> It miniſtred to their continual Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, that the God of Heaven was even riding in the heights of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to bring them to, and fix them in their own Land and City, and to enable them to compleat their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken Work. 4thly. It look'd great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at this great Profeſſor, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> himſelf: for his Profeſſion made it clear how much he valued himſelf, and promiſed to his People and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from his Relation to this God, and from the Conduct, Government, and Kindneſs of this God to him, whom he had choſen to carry on this Work. 5thly. It look'd greatly at their approaching Privileges and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Mercies; <hi>This is our God,</hi> who is the <hi>God of Heaven.</hi> And O the ſparklings of his heavenly Glory, which we ſhall ſee to our great Benefit and Pleaſure in the great Glories of his rebuilt Temple, and repaired Walls and City! 6thly. This look'd greatly at their preſent Work; for it was their own concocting and digeſting of all thoſe Miniſtries to their Courage and Endeavours, of which their Senſe of God was as the Life and Strength.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62163:18"/> Their Hearts would ſaint, their Hands grow feeble, their Thoughts would be confounded, their Expectations would be baffled, and their Spirits ſtript of Courage; were not all theſe reviv'd upon them by this great Name, which they ſo pertinently and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently profeſs'd. 7thly. This look'd greatly at their <hi>own endanger'd Frame.</hi> Their Enemies were many, they themſelves but few. Their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were crafty, buſy, and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, whereby they were but as Sheep amongſt the Wolves. But when they ſet this God againſt their Enemies, they readily could conclude, that all their Enemies would be found Liars, as to God and them. And, 8thly. It look'd as greatly at that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation which muſt be vigorouſly carried on in order to their getting, keeping, pleaſing, and honouring their God. They knew that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining of Mens Spirits, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of their Lives, were as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving Mountains, and as raiſing Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from the Dead. It is no eaſy Enterprize to oppoſe Sinners againſt their Intereſts, and againſt their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62163:18"/> ſtrong Corruptions; and to bring Men off from all their darling Luſts and Follies. But when they knew that the God of Heaven could make them ſtrong and proſperous; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever might appear exceeding diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, could not be thought impoſſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VI. The Doctrinal Import of this to us.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. That which the God of Heaven will proſper in their hands, his Servants ſhould reſolve on and promote. Be the thing enterprized never ſo difficult, coſtly, or unlikely to ſucceed in humane thought or view, yet if God order it, and expect it from us, as we are his Servants; and if he intimates his purpoſe to ſucceed us, we muſt not be diſcouraged or remiſs. This great and glorious Undertaking to repair the Temple, City, Walls, and to reform the People, how intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and perplexing was it found when once engag'd in by <hi>Zerubbabel, Joſhua, Ezra, Nehemiah,</hi> and all the Remnant of the People? Contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Scorners deſpis'd them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62163:19"/> them: Pretenders offer to work with them, with the greater Subtlety and Secreſy, to confound and hinder them: The People of the Land diſturb them, and hire Counſellors to fruſtrate this their purpoſe: Theſe (in confederacy with others) miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them to the King: and they provoke him to reverſe his Order iſſued out to build; and they accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly prevail. And thus the Work was made to ceaſe by Force and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. When they obtain'd a new Commiſſion from the God of Heaven (or rather the Revival of a former Order) by <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah,</hi> God's Prophets; this alſo was enquired into, cenſur'd, and inform'd againſt by <hi>Tatnai,</hi> and <hi>Shethar-Boznai:</hi> but yet the Elders kept up their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Purpoſe, and Profeſſion; and they went on boldly in their Work. After this they had mercenary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who by Prophecies and crafty Inſinuations of inſtant Enemies and Dangers, endeavour'd to obſtruct their Progreſs; and all this under great pretence of Friendſhip, tho they deſign'd hereby to influence
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62163:19"/> theſe Builders and Reformers into a Diſtruſt of God, a contracting a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to themſelves, and turning ſcandalous to the People: Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this, the Wall was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. And (if ſome ſay true) a Counter-Temple and Religion at <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> was adviſed to, to divide them: which was accordingly accompliſh'd, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us, <hi>Jud. Antiq. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. And <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> (who was Grandchild to <hi>Eliaſhib</hi> the High Prieſt, and Son-in-law to <hi>Sanballat</hi>) was made their Prieſt, by the Solicitation of <hi>Sanballat,</hi> that ſo <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> might not put away <hi>Sanballat</hi>'s Daughter, his Wife, as the Elders of the Jews required. See Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>'s <hi>Annal. ad Ann.</hi> 4381. <hi>ex Joſepho.</hi> Hence all revolted thither who would not quit their ſtrange Wives. From all this 'tis moſt evident, that theſe, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their Duty to God, and of their Encouragements from God, went on to build; and that they look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all their Enemies and Affronts but as the Trial of their Faith and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. And this, in the Doctrine of it, reaches us, who have this day diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62163:20"/> our Duty, and eſpous'd it; and who here preſent our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, to bewail the Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhments of our Walls and Temple, and our Reproaches conſequent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; to conſider and confeſs our Sins, whoſe Sinfulneſs is ſo viſible in theſe our Deſolations; to profeſs our concurrent ſolemn Reſolutions, to ſet upon Reparation-work; to intreat God's Bleſſing upon our purpoſed and commenced Reformations; and to make known to all, our Relation to God, our Confidence in him, our Zeal for him, our Dependence on him, and our great Expectations from him: and to teſtify to all, in whom, in what, and to what purpoſes we (tho differing in Sentiments as to ſome ſmaller things of ritual Conſideration and Concern) do now unite as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to love, encourage, and aſſiſt each other, <hi>as one in God and Chriſt,</hi> to run down Immoralities, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Men to that viſibly orderly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour which may conciliate to our Religion (our Chriſtianity) its juſt and genuine Reputation; and to make <hi>us Proteſtants</hi> more exemplary,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62163:20"/> and leſs ſcandalous even in the eyes of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf. And ſhall we be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by any thing, from attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to reſcue our profeſs'd Religion from the Reproaches of the Pagan, Antichriſtian, Papal World? What can be more <hi>of God</hi> than what is <hi>for him?</hi> And what can be more <hi>for God</hi> than what is <hi>of him?</hi> And when can we expect his Preſence, Patronage, Countenance, and our Succeſs from him, if <hi>not</hi> when we become all Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Vigour againſt what he hath ſo frequently and ſolemnly remonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto; and for what he hath told us, that he has prepared a Hell; and upon what he hath left upon Record, the Hiſtory of ſo many executed (and thoſe ſo very tremendous) Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? By which 'tis evident what he hath moſt eſpouſed, and doth ſo evidently ſet his Heart upon. No Man (I hope) of a greater Latitude and Candour for free Thoughts, and Searches, and Expreſſions, than my ſelf, when I ſee them attended with fit Modeſty and Self-ſuſpicion, and a true evident Concern for ſerious Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with God, and for practical
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62163:21"/> Chriſtian Godlineſs, in thoſe who differ from me in doubtful and inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our things. God himſelf knows how far I am diſtruſtful of my own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Weakneſs whereof doth coſt me many a ſerious, ſad, ſelf-hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Thought, in both my Solitudes and in Converſation. Yet other Mens Paſſions and diſcouraging Reflections upon me, will never make my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment better, tho they fill my Heart with Grief, and force me to lament my ſelf, and to refer them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to <hi>their</hi> Judg and <hi>mine.</hi> But yet I ſee no reaſon that bold-fac'd Atheiſm, Infidelity, Anti-ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turiſm, and the daring ridiculing of the Eternal Word and Son of God, ſhould eſcape their deſerved Cenſures, ſo far as liable thereunto by the Laws of God and Man. For of ſuch things I hear from others, tho I have met with none my ſelf. I would not have every Objection, modeſtly and diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offer'd, and cloſely urg'd in its full Strength in order to its fit Reſolution, to be accounted culpable. Modeſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries and Propoſals are vaſtly diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from induſtrious deſign'd Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62163:21"/> of Errors, and from ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and blaſphemous Reflections upon the Godhead of the Lord of Glory. So far as I can find, too much in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writ is <hi>attributed</hi> and aſcribed to Chriſt by <hi>God himſelf;</hi> too much is <hi>arrogated, claimed,</hi> and <hi>aſſumed</hi> by <hi>Chriſt</hi> unto <hi>himſelf;</hi> too much has been <hi>predicted</hi> of him by the <hi>Prophets;</hi> yea, and too much has been <hi>aſſerted, received, expected,</hi> and <hi>atteſted</hi> by his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> in their day, to leave it poſſible for me to think him a <hi>mere Creature,</hi> or any thing leſs than the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> and <hi>Son of God.</hi> To which I will take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to add, that how the Univerſal Government and Judgment ſhould be ſafely committed to and left with a mere Creature, or with one that could not judg the World without a Promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, quite exceeds my Underſtanding. But as to Blaſphemies, Profanations of Holy Days and Inſtitutions, abuſing thoſe who miniſter therein; Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Intemperance, carnal Pollutions, expoſing Sacred Words and Things to Scorn, unſeaſonable hauntings of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick-houſes; yea, all things tending to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62163:22"/> debauch Youth, or others, theſe God would have rebuked and expoſed to Puniſhment and Shame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. High Thoughts of God ſhould evermore attend great Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings for him. It is in his Name, for his Sake, to his Praiſe, and by his Order, that we go forth to ſerve him comfortably any way. Where then is our Confidence and Courage? Where is the Strength and Cogency of our Motives, if God be meanly thought on by us? He that miſrepreſents his God to himſelf, diſpirits all that is to move him to his Work; and dilutes every thing that is derived from God. We are not ſelf-ſufficient; our Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, Adverſaries, and Perplexities, will be found manifold and mighty. Perfidiouſneſs will be frequent. We our ſelves ſhall faint and be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, if our due Senſe of God do not animate our Endeavours. Whence otherwiſe can we derive our Conduct, Courage, Strength, Protection or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs? How can we think or hope to fetch down Gigantick Wickedneſs, or to ſtem the Tide of rampant Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62163:22"/> and Profaneneſs, (which hath ſo many ſubtle, potent, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Patrons and Abettors of it, who through long Cuſtom are hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therein) but by our dependence upon that God whoſe Name we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and adore? And how ſhall we preſerve our Bow in ſtrength, and invigorate our Purpoſes and Courage, to oppoſe Debauchery and Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but by our actuated Thoughts of our <hi>exalted</hi> God in our <hi>own</hi> Spirits; and by our ſetting off his Eminence againſt all the formidable Aſpects of Sin's Votaries and Champions; and againſt the diſcouraging Proſpects of that Coſt and Danger whereto our eſpouſed Enterprize may expoſe us?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. Great Expectations from God will give great Life and Spirit to noble Actions and Enterprizes for God. High Hopes will make our Spirits truly Heroick, and inſpire and fortify the braveſt Reſolutions for ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and great Actions and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts. God eyed as <hi>for us, near us,</hi> and <hi>before us,</hi> as with his <hi>Euge</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> will make us fearleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62163:23"/> and greatly eager in the purſuit of what concerns his Laws and Glory. Certain Acceptance and Succeſs muſt needs have cogent Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences upon conſiderate Souls. Lively Hopes make thorow Work: <hi>God will proſper, and therefore we will build.</hi> The God we hope to live with, and whom now we ſerve, hath neither Heart nor Heaven (we know) for Immorality. He is the God, and Heaven the State, and Holineſs the Frame and Courſe; and Chriſt the Patron; the Law of God the Rule; his Promiſes the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement; his Preſence, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and Spirit, the Promoters and Countenancers of all due Order, and of all beautiful Converſation: And <hi>Satan</hi> is the Enemy, and Hell the Sink and End of all that is againſt this. He therefore that expects the Patronage and Kindneſs of his God, and that underſtands wherein theſe muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and fix, here and hereafter, will heartily endeavour the extirpation of all things irreceptive of God's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and Reward. They that make God their All, that have placed their Hearts in Heaven, and know
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62163:23"/> the ſtated Laws of Expectation: They that have well conſidered the Repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of Sin unto, and its Inconſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence with the holy Nature, Will, and Intereſt of God; with the true Health, the great Beauty and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Pleaſure of humane Souls; with the due Grandeur and Deſigns of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Government; (which is indeed the Illuſtration of Divine Excellencies in the true Conſtitution and Conduct of what relates unto the Sons of Men, ſutably to their Author, Make, Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and End) <hi>theſe,</hi> as they expect Succeſs in what is <hi>of</hi> and <hi>for</hi> this God, ſo will they engage and act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 4. What we believe, expect, and purpoſe, with reſpect to God, ſhould be as freely owned and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by us, as others teſtify their Scorns and Enmity againſt God. <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. Great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes ought to be ſeconded with brisk and bold Profeſſion when the caſe requires it. <hi>Ezra</hi> 5.11, 12. Thus in the Text, <hi>Then anſwered I them,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16—18. Mind here what
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62163:24"/> was profeſs'd: 1ſt. That <hi>their God</hi> was the <hi>God of Heaven;</hi> but ſo was not the God of their Enemies. 2dly. That <hi>they were the Servants of this God;</hi> and thus were their <hi>Enemies Gods</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed. 3dly. That they were <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to build for God:</hi> And thus the <hi>Oppoſitions</hi> of their idolatrous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were (in the ſober Senſe of God) confronted by them. 4thly. That the <hi>God of Heaven would proſper them.</hi> Thus were their <hi>Enemies,</hi> and <hi>their Gods</hi> deſpiſed by them, as too impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to help or hinder them. 5thly. All this was <hi>boldly owned</hi> by them when moſt <hi>deſpiſed</hi> and <hi>derided</hi> by their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and thoſe too ſome of the <hi>greateſt</hi> of them. And thus their Scorn and Rage were repreſented to their faces as moſt deſpicable things, becauſe of the Patronage of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Being. What may juſtify your Work, will equally juſtify your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and Profeſſion. Shall we not be as bold for God as others are againſt him? Where lie the odds? <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.26—29. <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.6, 7.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:62163:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 5. Our Purpoſes and Practices ought to agree with our Relations, Stations, and Profeſſions; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.9. This <hi>great Reformer</hi> gives the Anſwer, makes the Profeſſion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms the People, incourages the Work, addreſſes to and eyes his God, rebukes the Immoralities of his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, brings them to obſerve, and own, and praiſe their God, in the Advances of their Work. And he acts anſwerably to his <hi>Station,</hi> as a <hi>Magiſtrate;</hi> to his <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> as a <hi>rich Man;</hi> to his <hi>Relation,</hi> as <hi>God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant;</hi> to his <hi>Obligations,</hi> as the Surviver of a long Captivity; as attended with <hi>gracious Providences,</hi> and as his <hi>Prince's Favourite,</hi> to the beſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage both of Church and State.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VII. Practical Reflections on the whole.</head>
               <p n="1">1. See hence who are the fitteſt Perſons to appear and act for God: Thoſe that are <hi>hearty Servants:</hi> Thoſe that have <hi>great Thoughts of God:</hi> And thoſe that moſt <hi>depend of God</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62163:25"/> for their <hi>Conduct, Protection,</hi> and <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. See hence what ſuch are moſt intent upon: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.5, 6. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 2—8. <hi>Neh.</hi> 2 3. Building for God, and for his People; doing what may diſtinguiſh, credit, and ſecure <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and God's Worſhip, Truth, and People there: and indeed nothing but what may well become the Patronage, Preſence, and Incouragements of the God of Heaven. <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.11—13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. See hence what <hi>actuated Thoughts</hi> of God, and of <hi>fit Confidence</hi> in him, and of <hi>great Expectations</hi> from him, will make Men do: <hi>viz.</hi> theſe will fix their Purpoſes, fire their Zeal for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Behaviour, ſpirit their Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, embolden their Looks and Speeches, and make God's Servants keep their ground, and to mind their hits and helps.</p>
               <p n="4">4. See hence how a few Men of Place and Figure, by their exemplary Wiſdom, Zeal and Diligence, may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the Body of a People. They may be as their <hi>Eye,</hi> their <hi>Heart,</hi> their <hi>Hand,</hi> and <hi>Mouth.</hi> We ſee how <hi>Nehemiah</hi> could ſpeak as in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62163:25"/> Name of all, and for them; and draw the reſt after him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. See hence what it is to appear and act for God, and for the Good of his <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> from <hi>Principles of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>Religion. Self</hi> is here laid aſide, and melted down into the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Order of the Publick, even of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> It is not well with ſuch in their own Thoughts, unleſs and until Publick Affairs go proſperouſly on. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.5, 6.</p>
               <p n="6">6. See hence what a true Eſtimate of God's City, and of his Temple-preſence there, will prompt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile his Servants to: Nothing is thought too great, too good, too much, as to Diligence, Coſt, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, Watchfulneſs, and Adventures, to ſet all right towards God and Man; to reform Mens Lives and Manners, that thus God and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may delightfully dwell together. This ſpeaks the God of Heaven, well known, and greatly valued by his People.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:62163:26"/>
               <head>VIII. A word of Exhortation to Reformers, and that to theſe few things.</head>
               <p n="1">1. To <hi>Conſiderateneſs.</hi> Luke 14.28—32. and that in ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: 1ſt. As to <hi>your God.</hi> For 'tis for him that you ariſe and build: <hi>bis</hi> you are; <hi>for him</hi> you enterprize your preſent Work; <hi>under his Eye</hi> you are at work; <hi>to him</hi> you are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; <hi>according to his Order</hi> you muſt act; <hi>on him</hi> you muſt attend and bear your ſelves; <hi>to him</hi> you muſt reſort; and <hi>from himſelf</hi> muſt you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive your fit Reward. Think then <hi>with what a God</hi> you have to do; <hi>whoſe Preſence</hi> you deſire and prepare for; <hi>whoſe Work</hi> you are about; and <hi>to whoſe Will and Service</hi> you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this diſſolute, profane, debauch'd, immoral Generation. 2dly. As <hi>to your ſelves.</hi> Conſider well <hi>from what Principles</hi> you act; <hi>what</hi> you have in your Eye as your great Deſign and Scope; <hi>by what Rule</hi> you intend to walk; and then <hi>what Life</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> is put into your ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62163:26"/> weighty and warrantable Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. 3dly. As to your <hi>enterprized Work before you:</hi> Ruins here call for Lamentation; Breaches for Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Rubbiſh for Rejection; Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for Watchfulneſs; long, tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and much Work, for Patience; Scoffs and Conflicts for great Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; different Humours, Stations, Circumſtances, and Degrees and Kinds of Crimes, for much Wiſdom and Diſcretion; ſubtile Countermines, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions and Excuſes, for ſerious, prudent, deep and clear Diſcoveries and Thoughts; and all your Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures and Succeſſes, for Obſervations and Acknowledgments. And ſeeing ſo many Eyes may be fix'd upon you, what ſtrict Self-diſcipline and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Blameleſſneſs ought you to have? And I need not tell you, what neceſſity is incumbent on you for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn frequent Prayer to God, for your Conduct, Safety, Incouragement, and Succeſs from him in this Concern. Here then conſider well what you may ask and urge; and how you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and uſe what ſuch Addreſſes may bring in.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62163:27"/>2. <hi>To Confidence in God.</hi> That you ſhall not be Loſers, nor deſerted by him in this thing. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.13. The <hi>God of Heaven</hi> will help you. The <hi>Son of God</hi> will ſpeak and plead for you. The <hi>Spirit of God</hi> will cheriſh and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame what he implants and kindles in you. For all the Immoralities which you are labouring to ſuppreſs, are grievous to him, and a great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to his Work. <hi>God's Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> will not neglect you. You have <hi>(caeteris paribus)</hi> the <hi>Proſpect</hi> and <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of your Great Maſter's <hi>Euge</hi> and <hi>Reward.</hi> True <hi>Peace of Conſcience</hi> will attend you in theſe your reſolute and regular Purpoſes and Engagements for your God. The very <hi>Conſciences of the Diſſolute</hi> are againſt themſelves for you; and their future <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>State</hi> will juſtify your Zeal and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs at Death, or in the day of Judgment. God will be every way your Friend; and they that know his Name may chearfully and ſafely truſt him in his way. <hi>Set but your God before you always, and you need not be moved.</hi> O let not theſe incouraging Conſolations be neglected, unconcoct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62163:27"/> indigeſted, or accounted ſmall! Your ſolemn Thoughts muſt help your Confidence; your Confidence muſt ſix your Purpoſe, and quicken you to and in your Work. Did we but make more reckoning of God, as the <hi>God of Heaven,</hi> and as <hi>our God,</hi> he would more gloriouſly ſhew himſelf for us. There would be more Experience of him undoubtedly, were there more regular and actuated Expectation from him; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.3, 4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>To Reſolution for God.</hi> Acts 11.23. <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.11. And let thoſe Words of Truth and Soberneſs be well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, which you find in <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5—11. Fix'd and ſtrong Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is as the Root and Life of generous and great Actions. I verily perſwade my ſelf, that I ſpeak to Principles when I ſpeak to you. I am (I hope) both a Stranger and an Enemy to Flattery. So far as I can underſtand, this glorious and hopeful Project was no ſooner contrived, eſpouſed, and ſet on foot by Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as to their ſtated Communion, and <hi>ſuch</hi> in <hi>Faithfluneſs to their own Judgment,</hi> than it was
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62163:28"/> readily complied with by others called <hi>Diſſenters:</hi> but we are all one in Chriſt, and Members each of other. And being now concentred in this great Purpoſe and Concern, I hope we ſhall go on, both hand in hand, and heart in heart; and make it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all, that our different Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſome other Matters will not extinguiſh or abate reciprocal Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Reſpects, nor make any Breaches or Incroachments upon any fit Civilities of Converſation; nor upon any Articles of mutual Helpful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as to the Publick Good, or our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Concerns with one another. Such large and noble Souls are lovely things indeed, both in the ſight of God and Man, as can make all yield to weighty things, and make us can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly and reſpectfully to converſe and act together, to ſtem that Tide of Wickedneſs and Profaneneſs which threatens ſo apparently to ruin the Welfare and Renown of Church and State. See <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.1—3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.8—16. &amp; 5.5, 27—29. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. Bold Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and an angry God; great Crimes attended with notorious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitencies,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62163:28"/> and growthful Judgments, are dreadful things when found toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.26—28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2—6. Let then your Fear of God, and your Pity to the Land, and to the Souls of Men, excite and fix you.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To your mutual ſtrengthning of each others Hands in this great Work and Purpoſe; <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24. You have great Incouragements from God and Chriſt, from Heaven and Earth, from the Laws of God and Man, and from the publick Profeſſions of Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, who ſtand up at the Creed; who cry, <hi>Incline our Hearts to keep this Law;</hi> and that in ſolemn Aſſemblies; and who do not deny <hi>that God, that Chriſt, that Goſpel,</hi> which teſtify and proteſt againſt the very Crimes which they ſo ſhameleſly commit and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate. None ſo deſerving of Rebukes and Puniſhments from God, as they that ſin againſt the very Letter of thoſe Laws which they profeſs to be Divine, and which are no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted amongſt themſelves. Set but their profeſſed Principles againſt thoſe their Practices, which contradict ſuch Principles; ſhew but the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62163:29"/> of theſe Mens Principles and Practices with one another; and then urge them cloſely, to ſhew to all which of theſe two muſt be deſerted and denied by them. We may put Spirit thus into each other, and God will own and patronize us all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To diſcourage all thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Doctrines (as far as regularly you can) which miniſter to theſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moralities. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9—16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Jude</hi> 3, 4. He that ſhall teach, There is no God, no Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, no future Judgment, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently neither Heaven nor Hell: He that ſhall propagate ſuch Doctrines as theſe, that Souls are mortal; that Chriſt is not the Son of God; that Man is but a ſiner ſort of Brute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he ought to be ſtopp'd in ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reers. For if theſe be true, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited accordingly, then all Religion and Morality comes down at once. All <hi>then</hi> muſt be <hi>lawful</hi> that may be <hi>ſafely</hi> done, as to humane Vices and Injuriouſneſs.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To walk prudently and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly your ſelves in all things. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.14, 15. <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.9. it is but reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62163:29"/> for you to expect all ſorts of Eyes upon you. They whom you proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute for their Immoralities, will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be awakened and irritated to their ſeverer Obſervations of you. And ſhould they (which I hope they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will, and beg of God and you they never may) ever find you guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſame Sins, or of equivalent Crimes to what you proceed againſt them for, you may conclude that your Miſcarriages will be <hi>told in Gath,</hi> with all imaginable Aggravations, to your Reproach, and to their Joy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God himſelf will juſtly make you baſe before the People; in that as God and others expected other things from you, ſo may you look for ſuch Returns upon you from his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed and incenſed (becauſe more reproached) Majeſty, as ſhall abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly demonſtrate, that <hi>with him there is no reſpect of Perſons;</hi> and that <hi>your Profeſſion of God and Chriſt, and your Endeavours to ſuppreſs Sin in others, ſhall not commute for your diſhonouring of God, and for your being ſcandalous unto others,</hi> by your own perſonal Tranſgreſſions. Nor is your perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62163:30"/> Blameleſſneſs, as to Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſufficient for you in this matter, but you muſt alſo ſee that all your Diligence, Zeal and Courage, have their due Conduct, and be every way (as far as in you lies) accountable to God and Man. Bear with me in this faithful Freedom with you: This Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not given you from Accuſation or Suſpicion of any one amongſt you. All that is poſſible doth not come to paſs; but you are Men, and in the World and Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IX. A word to the Immoral and Profane.</head>
               <p>Could I intreat you ſeriouſly to read <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.9—26. and <hi>there</hi> and <hi>then</hi> conſider the <hi>Sins</hi> there doomed to a ſolemn publick Curſe; the <hi>God</hi> who hates thoſe <hi>Sins,</hi> and who will exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Curſe where-ever he ſees thoſe Sins committed; the <hi>Motive</hi> offered and urged there; and <hi>God's inſiſting upon univerſal Obedience</hi> to his Laws, with the Encouragements which he affords thereto, in <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.1—13. Could I obtain of you to lay to heart
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62163:30"/> that peremptory Word, with the hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical occaſion of it, in <hi>Levit.</hi> 24. 10—16. <hi>Whoſoever curſeth his God ſhall bear his Sin: and he that blaſphemeth the Name of the Lord ſhall die.</hi> Could I prevail with you to pauſe upon God's <hi>publiſhed</hi> Reſolution, <hi>not to hold him guiltleſs</hi> (not to free him from his Wrath) <hi>who taketh his Name in vain,</hi> Exod. 20.7. I might then hope that your Reverence towards God, and your Self-love and Care might keep you orderly and ſafe. Uncleanneſs, Intemperance, Rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Profaneneſs, are ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing and unworthy things, as that ſerious Thoughts could not but move you to abhor them. Are not your Tongues, your Souls and Bodies, <hi>his, who made and bought them?</hi> Were they created and redeemed; Are they protected, maintained, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated, and encouraged, to be alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from their Proprietor, and to be profaned and abuſed before him? Can any thing be pleaded for your Sins which may be juſtified at your own Tribunal? Or can the Gain and Pleaſure of your Crimes compenſate
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62163:31"/> what you are ſure to loſe, and to bring upon your ſelves thereby? If there be no God, no future State, how came you by your Beings, and by all your ſutable Proviſions for their univerſal Welfare? But if there be a God, and a future State, hath he made <hi>that</hi> and <hi>you</hi> to be eternally his own Reproach? Or do you think God made his Laws in vain? Or that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven can bear or ſute with your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Frame and Courſe? Or that God <hi>needs</hi> or <hi>fears</hi> you, ſo as to ſave you, with a Lie in his own Mouth, or to confront him in the Heavenly State; or to let you provoke him whilſt you live here, and then to change you, and to ſave you when you die? Your Reformation will be your Credit and Safety, and our great Eaſe and Joy.</p>
               <p>It can be no way pleaſing to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Mind, or to Men of Peace, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent upon their own Intereſt, Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Safety <hi>here,</hi> to miniſter to Contentions, or to irritate your Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by thwarting and expoſing you to publick Cenſures, or by reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, tho in ſecret; were they not conſcious to themſelves of theſe things,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62163:31"/> of <hi>God's ſtrict Obſervations</hi> both of them and you; of the <hi>accurate Laws</hi> by which he will judg us all; of the <hi>Solemnity</hi> and <hi>Impartiality</hi> of that Judgment; of the <hi>Importance</hi> of the future State to all; of the <hi>terrible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>views</hi> and <hi>Cenſures</hi> which <hi>your</hi> and <hi>their</hi> awakened Conſciences, (by the ſo ſenſible Approaches and Inſtancy of <hi>Eternity</hi> on a Death-bed, <hi>wherein</hi> we can look for nothing but the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities of Divine Revenges) will make upon all Follies and Neglects: Of thoſe moſt <hi>intimate</hi> and <hi>ſharp Reſentments</hi> which our Great Judg cannot but have of all your notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and aggravated Crimes, which have ſo boldly and provokingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted him in the whole Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Procedures of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Deſigns: Of ſome <hi>poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of reclaiming you,</hi> and of <hi>redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing you to God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and of the <hi>notice</hi> which God and Chriſt will take of them, as they behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this Affair towards you. They do believe the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith. They know thoſe Rules of holy and orderly Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62163:32"/> towards God, themſelves, and others, by which they muſt be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned and judged. They are very apprehenſive of their Sacramental Vows and Ties to be true to God and Chriſt, and you. They have ſeen the tragical and diſmal Concluſions of debauched and immoral Lives. They clearly do diſcern the dreadful Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of ſuch Lives upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace and Welfare. They are not ignorant of thoſe moſt rueful Deſolations of Perſons, Families, Churches, Kingdoms and Societies, which diſſolute Spirits and Practices have produced and multiplied. And they are well ſatisfied that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention or Removal of God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the procuring and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of his bleſſing Preſence with us, can never rationally be expected but in the way of univerſal penitent Reformation, and evident Return to God. And they would be glad to know but in what Frame and Mirrour you would behold and face your ſelves. Do but reflect upon <hi>what you are:</hi> And can you think it orderly and accountable (even to your own
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62163:32"/> impartial ſelves) that Men ſhould brutify themſelves? That rational Souls ſhould proſtitute their ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Faculties and Powers to the ſo ſordid and mean Intereſts and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions of intemperate Fleſh? Shall that lie wallowing in the Mire, with the Self-defiling Brute, which might ſo gratefully and commendably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert and illuſtrate its own Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Vigours in the due Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of its ſo very uſeful Body? <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Intemperance</hi> are a great profanation of that ſo curiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and compacted Manſion which is conſigned to the Soul to live in, and to improve, to its own true and great Advantage. And for the <hi>Tongue,</hi> which is the Soul's Orator and Interpreter, to repreſent its <hi>Excellence</hi> and <hi>Senſe of things</hi> to all; muſt <hi>that</hi> be uſed to viler Purpoſes, even to proclaim your Transforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into a deviliſh Frame and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Doth it become a Creature to blaſpheme and curſe its God, to imprecate his Anger, to contend with the Author of it ſelf, and to ſhew more Enmity and leſs Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62163:33"/> to him, than Pagans will or dare to do unto their falſe Gods? What need of Oaths and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in humane Converſation! Such things are no ways fitly expreſſive of noble Extraction, of genteel Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, of improved Parts, of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Learning, or of endearing Principles and Diſpoſitions; nor yet of conſiderable Uſefulneſs and Figure in Church or State.</p>
               <p>Do but reflect upon <hi>whoſe you are.</hi> You are <hi>God's own,</hi> as to <hi>Property, Obligation,</hi> and <hi>Accountableneſs,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will or no: Nor can you diveſt him of his Right to uſe you as he pleaſes; tho you may poſſibly ſpoil your Title, and implead all Claims unto his Favour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. And now, muſt that be uſed againſt him which is more <hi>His</hi> than Yours? Or can you think your ſelves to be of ſuch Ability and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, as to hector, curſe, or flatter him out of his own Throne and Rights? Can you implead his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Sentence, or prevent its exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, when doomed by him to Hell?</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62163:33"/>
               <p>Do but reflect upon <hi>where you are;</hi> even in that <hi>World</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you have not long to ſtay; but you have much to do and be, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to your everlaſting Miſery or Happineſs. This World is but a Pilgrim-ſtate. Your Fleſh is as the Graſs or Shadow. Your carnal Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are but Dotages, Dreams, and Snares. Your Blaſphemies, Curſings, Oaths, and rants of Speech; your ſwelling Words of Vanity are but Self-cruelty and Reproach, and the haſtening and enflaming of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance, which, when inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on you, will convince you to the purpoſe, of how unfit a Match you are for an incenſed and ingaged God againſt you. Your bold Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts to God and Chriſt, ſpeak you either ignorant of, or unacquainted with, and inconſiderate about <hi>your ſelves</hi> and <hi>Them.</hi> Nor can I think on any thing whereto you can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe your preſent Peace, but to your contracted and judicial Stupid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; which is, I think, the greateſt Plague on this ſide Hell. Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſs and Fearleſſneſs are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62163:34"/> of Careleſſneſs and Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Theſe ripen Souls apace for Hell; and they will be found as the drying of the Stubble for the Flames of the infernal Pit, wherein the Terrors of Revenges will ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and ſcorch ſuch Sinners moſt ſeverely. And ſhall this preſent State, and Scantling of probationary time only be ſpent in what is moſt like to ſhorten it, to ruin you, to ſtrike profanely at both Majeſty and Mercy, and to prevent your own Salvation, by making it unbecoming God and Chriſt to ſave you from eternal Wrath? And ſhall others fear or love you more than they love God and Chriſt? And muſt they tamely give up all God's Rights, leſt you ſhould thereby be diſpleaſed and ſtopt (tho regularly) in your attempted Rapes upon all that is Orderly and Sacred? You know your time is ſhort; that it is given you by God, purchaſed by Chriſt, and filled with what may help you to a better State. And is this the beſt Improvement of what you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with ſo kindly, to curſe and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62163:34"/> ſwear, to profane Holy Time and Things, and to drench your ſelves in ſuch prodigious Filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, who are to perfect Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the fear of God? O tell us ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, or ask your ſelves in your ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Thoughts; to whom, to what, are you thus moſt attempered? Think you that there is ſo little difference betwixt God and Satan, Heaven and Hell, as that the Spirit and Practice of the one can be congenial with the other? Think therefore moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedly upon <hi>Who it is that inſtigates and prompts you to all your Diſſoluteneſs and Profaneneſs, and why he burries you hereto, and animates thoſe Principles in you, whereby he governs you for himſelf.</hi> Doth Satan love your God, your Souls, your Happineſs? When you have by him filled your meaſure up, and at length find your ſelves in Hell; will that malignant and proud Enemy in Hell, (<hi>the Devil</hi> I mean) forget or pardon all your Reflections upon him? or will he overlook any thing done by you in time diſſerviceable to himſelf? He knows you never can be <hi>his,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you caſt off holy Speeches, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62163:35"/> and Practices, and yield your ſelves to be his obedient Servants, and to become his Voluntiers. Are others then your Enemies becauſe they would reſcue you from him? And laſtly, ſpend ſome ſolemn and cloſe Thoughts on this, <hi>viz. What you are like to think of your own ſelf-ruined ſelves.</hi> When God is your fixed Enemy: when Chriſt hath ſentenced you to Hell: when Angels have bound you up, and have thrown you thither: when all this World is burnt and gone: when you have ſeen Chriſt's Family carried up with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Glory, and find your ſelves, after an awful Trial, ſhut out for ever, and given up to the abſolute Pleaſure of your inſulting Enemy: when Conſcience, Paſſions, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges are let looſe to fix torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and to center on your deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and remedileſs ſelves: and when your free Thoughts are to range in the Diſcoveries of all thoſe Springs of Miſery, of which once you took ſo little notice here. When theſe things are upon you in their eternal Strength and Fulneſs, can you then face, or have Converſes with your profane,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62163:35"/> debauched, intemperate, wilful, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted and diſtracted ſelves, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully? Or can you think that Chriſt will fetch thoſe Souls to Heaven, that always practically and preſumptuouſly told him how little they eſteem'd Heaven or Him? and how much they preferred Satan and his Ways there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? I have no perſonal Prejudice againſt any of you. I highly value your Learning, Parts and Ingenuities, and Uſefulneſs, and all things valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in you. And O that your ſpeedy and effectual Reformation might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all things diſgraceful and afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you!</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62163:36"/>
            <head>Books printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Body of Practical Divinity, containing 176 Sermons on the Aſſemblies leſſer Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm. By <hi>Tho. Watſon,</hi> formerly Miniſter of St. <hi>Stephens Walbrook, London. Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sermons and Diſcourſes on ſeveral Divine Subjects, by the late Reverend and Learned <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid Clarkſon,</hi> B. D. and ſome time Fellow of <hi>Clare-hall, Cambridge. Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s Annotations upon the Holy Bible, in two Volumes, <hi>Fol.</hi> The third Edition, with an Addition of a Concordance, and Contents to each Chapter. By Mr. <hi>Sam. Clark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theological Diſcourſes, in 8 Letters, and 3 Sermons on the Sacred Trinity: Part the 1ſt. 4to. Theological Diſcourſes and Sermons on ſeveral Occaſions: Part the 2d. 4to. Both by <hi>John Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> D.D. Profeſſor of Geometry in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mediocria:</hi> Or the Middle-way between Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant and Papiſt, in a Paper of Juſtification. The 2d Edition, with Additions of a Letter to Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi> 4to.</p>
            <p>Peaceable Diſquiſitions, in ſome Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on a Diſcourſe writ againſt Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Book of the Holy Spirit. 4to.</p>
            <p>Pacification touching the Doctrinal Diſſent among our United Brethren.</p>
            <p>The Righteouſneſs of God revealed in the Goſpel: Or, an impartial Enquiry into the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the great, but much controverted Article of Juſtification. To
<pb facs="tcp:62163:36"/> which are prefixed the Epiſtles of the Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend the Biſhops of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Cheſter.</hi> Theſe four by Mr. <hi>John Humfrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The glorious Reward of faithful Miniſters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and improved, in a Sermon upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Funeral of that excellent Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Henry Newcomb,</hi> A. M. late Paſtor of a Congregation at <hi>Mancheſter.</hi> By <hi>John Chorlton.</hi> 4to.</p>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon on the Death of that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentlewoman Mrs. <hi>Judith Hammond,</hi> late Wife of the Reverend Mr. <hi>George Hammond,</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel in <hi>London.</hi> By Mr. <hi>John Howe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at St. <hi>Mildred Poultrey, Jan.</hi> 3. 1696/7. by <hi>John</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and late Rector of the ſaid Church, upon his leaving the ſaid Pariſh.</p>
            <p>The Fountain of Life opened: Or, a Diſplay of Chriſt in his Eſſential and Mediatorial Glory, containing 42 Sermons on various Texts. 4to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pneumatologia:</hi> Or, a Treatiſe of the Soul of Man, 4to. Both by Mr. <hi>John Flavel,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Dartmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcourſes upon the rich Man and <hi>Lazarus.</hi> By <hi>Tim. Cruſo.</hi> 8vo.</p>
            <p>The Swearers Doom: Or, a Diſcourſe ſetting forth the great Sinfulneſs and Danger of vain and raſh Swearing: By <hi>John Roſt,</hi> A.M. Rector of <hi>Ofſwel</hi> and <hi>Gittiſham</hi> in <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Scripture-Light about the Goſpel-Ordinance of Baptiſm, in a Letter to ſome ſcrupulous Friends, by a ſincere Lover of the Chriſtian Community. 12mo.</p>
            <p>The Church-Catechiſm enlarged and explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:62163:37"/> in at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Method; with the Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and faithful Servant ſet forth, in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Oak</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> before the funeral of Mr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> some time Miniſter of the Goſpel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> account fo his Life and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. By <hi>Henry</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>A Paraphraſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with Notes, Doctrinall and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for the Uſe of religious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> calling of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Reverend Mr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> corrected. 8vo.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our Righteouſneſs: Or the Juſtification of Believers by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and applied in ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and Miniſter of the Goſpel. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Families with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Golden S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fers: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtian Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Reformers characterized, cautioned and encouraged a Sermon preached to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties for Reformation of Manners in <hi>London.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God's Being, and of the Scriptures Divine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 20 Directions for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of them. By <hi>D. Burgeſs.</hi> 8vo.</p>
            <p>A moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> explanation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhorter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> amended. By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Henry,</hi> Miniſter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Shropſhire</hi> who died June 29, 1696. fiftie fifth Year of his Age. Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by Dr. <hi>Bates.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
